快点干完活！
Finish work!
到棚屋去
Go to hut.
是啊 要不让新来的俘虏
Yeah, that figures.
看到我们在挖坟墓 他们会要逃跑的
If the new prisoners see us digging graves, they may run.
没时间说笑了 快点干！
No time for jokes. Finish work!
挖 挖
Dig, dig.
把我们算作病号 怎么样？
How about putting us on sick list?
发发慈悲吧 上尉 把我们放到医院里吧
Have a heart, captain. Put us in hospital.
你现在没有病 你从来没有病
You no sick. You never sick.
你为什么一直要装病 舍尔斯？
Why you always play sick, Shears?
我猜我不想放个这玩意儿在我头顶上
Don't want one of these over my head, I guess.
金松上尉…
Captain Kanematsu...
…烟屁股怎么样？
...how about a butt?
我今早才给你的 给你们俩
I give you butt this morning. Both of you.
是的 我不是那意思 我想回报一下
That's what I mean. I want to return the favour.
当一个好心人给我礼物…
When a man gives a gift from the goodness of his heart...
…就像你给我那烟屁股 我会牢记在心的
...like you gave me that butt, I remember it from the heart.
这就是为什么…
That's why...
…我想给你这打火机
...l want you to keep this lighter.
以为是我偷的？
Think I stole it?
这是我们刚刚埋的那个英国小伙子的
It belonged to that English kid we just buried.
是他感激我而送给我的
He gave it to me for a favour I'd done him.
在我死前 我想把它送给你
Before I pass on, I want to do the same for you.
你这个人真有趣 舍尔斯
You funny man, Shears.
你现在是病号了 他也是
You go on sick list. Him too.
总有一天 Saito 上校会发现你在贿赂他…
One of these days Colonel Saito will catch you bribing him...
…那时我们会怎么样？
...then where'll we be?
在那之前 我们早就离开这里了 伙计
Before that happens we'll be far away from here, chum.
逃得远远的
Far away.
好吧 我们收工吧
Okay, let's knock off.
这里躺着…
Here lies....
我忘掉了我们刚才埋的是谁
I forgot who we just buried.
汤姆森
Thomson.
啊 对
Ah, yes.
这里躺着赫伯特 汤姆森下士…
Here lies Corporal Herbert Thomson...
…编号是:01234567
...serial number zero- one- two-  three- four- five- six- seven.
国王或女王或着什么的勇敢的战士…
Valiant member of the King's Own or the Queen's Own or something...
…在我主纪元1943 死于脚气病…
...who died of beri- beri in the year of our Lord, 1 943...
…为了光荣伟大的…
...for the greater glory of....
- 他是为了什么死的？ - 算了
- What did he die for? - Come off it.
不要嘲笑死人
No need to mock the grave.
我没有嘲笑死人
I don't mock the grave or the man.
希望他能在和平中安息
May he rest in peace.
虽然在他活着的时候没有找到和平
He found little of it while he was alive.
A 队 原地踏步走！
"A" Company, mark time!
原地踏步走！
Mark time!
立定
Halt.
排成一行 向左转
Into line, left turn.
稍息
Stand easy.
我们又要挖很多墓 维佛
We're going to be busy gravediggers, Weaver.
干的好 干的好
Well done, well done.
那个上校还不知道他将会遭遇到什么
That colonel doesn't know what he's in for.
你准备去告诉他真相？
You going to tell him the truth?
当然不
Of course not.
你既不是军官也不是个绅士
You're neither an officer nor a gentleman.
我叫 尼科尔森
My name is Nicholson.
我是Saito 上校
I am Colonel Saito.
我以天皇的名义…
In the name of His lmperial Majesty...
…欢迎你们
...l welcome you.
我是这个战俘营的指挥官…
I am the commanding officer of this camp...
…这里是沿着这条大铁路…
...which is Camp 1 6...
…的第16战俘营…
...along the great railroad...
…这条铁路很快就将曼谷和仰光连接起来
...which will soon connect Bangkok with Rangoon.
你们这些英军俘虏…
You British prisoners have been chosen...
…将要去修建一座跨越桂河的大桥
...to build a bridge across the River Kwai.
这将是一个愉快的工作 但需要技能
It will be pleasant work, requiring skill.
军官也要和士兵一起工作
And officers will work as well as men.
我们小日本军队不会养吃白饭的懒人
The Japanese Army cannot have idle mouths to feed.
如果你努力工作 就会得到优待
If you work hard, you will be treated well.
但是如果你不努力工作…
But if you do not work hard...
…你将受到惩罚
...you will be punished.
关于逃跑 我要说几句
A word to you about escape.
这里没有铁丝网
There is no barbed wire.
没有围栏
No stockade.
也没有了望哨
No watchtower.
这些都不需要
They are not necessary.
我们处于热带雨林中一个孤岛
We are an island in the jungle.
逃出去是不可能的
Escape is impossible.
会死在雨林中的
You would die.
今天休息 明天开始干活
Today you rest. Tomorrow you'll begin.
最后让我告诉你们山下将军的格言:
Let me remind you of General Yamashita's motto:
"在工作中寻求快乐"
" Be happy in your work."
在工作中寻求快乐
Be happy in your work.
解散
Dismissed.
全体 稍息
Battalion, stand at ease.
出队 休斯上校
Fall out, Major Hughes.
全体 稍息
Battalion, stand easy.
休斯 把他们带到岗位上去 看看谁生病了
Hughes, get the men to their quarters. See who's sick.
我要和这家伙说句话
I'm going to have a word with this fellow.
我刚才听了你的训话 先生
I heard your remarks just now, sir.
我的部下会坚持英国士兵的一贯方式
My men will carry on in the way one expects of a British soldier.
我的军官和我会对他们的行为负责
My officers and I will be responsible for their conduct.
你可能没注意到让军官去劳动…
You may have overlooked the fact that the use of officers for labour...
…在日内瓦公约中是不允许的
...is expressly forbidden by the Geneva Convention.
是那样的吗？
Is that so?
我有一份公约的复印件…
I have a copy of the convention...
…我很乐意让你看一下
...and would be glad to let you glance through it.
不用了
That will not be necessary.
请坐
Sit down, please.
是 长官
Yes, sir.
我要和科林普顿说句话
I'm going to have a word with Clipton.
科林普顿 不要让别人打扰我
Clipton, don't let me interrupt.
- 胳膊怎么样了？ - 快好了
- How's the arm? - Nearly healed.
先生 这是美国海军的舍尔斯司令官
Sir, this is Commander Shears of the United States Navy.
你好 先生
How do you do, sir?
我们发现他和一个澳大利亚人
We found him and an Australian.
是修建这个营地的仅存俘虏
All that's left of the prisoners who built the camp.
美国海军？ 大老远的跑到这里？
U.S. Navy? Out here?
我们差不多被陆地包围了
I am sort of landlocked.
- 然后你丢弃了你的船？ - 休斯顿号
- You lost your ship? - The Houston.
我让它搁浅 但是我和其他的幸存者失散了
I made it ashore, but I got separated from the other survivors.
这儿原来和你在一起的人呢？
And your group here?
多数是澳洲人 一些…
Mostly Aussies. Some lime...
英国人还有印度人 缅甸人 暹罗人
Some British. Indians, Burmese, Siamese.
他们怎么了？
And what happened to them?
他们都死于…
They died...
…疟疾 痢疾 脚气和坏疽
...of malaria, dysentery, beri- beri, gangrene.
其他的死因是:
Other causes of death:
饥饿 劳累过度 枪伤 蛇咬…
Famine, overwork, bullet wounds, snakebites...
…还有 Saito
...Saito.
然后还有一些不想过了
Then there were some who just got tired of living.
科林普顿给你检查过了吗？
Has Clipton seen you?
正好就要看了 过来 你可以待会刮脸
Just about to. Come over here, you can shave later.
好的
All right.
你可以和军官待在一起
You'll stay with the officers.
我们会给你找一些象样的衣服
We'll find some decent clothing.
不要为我操心了
Don't bother about me.
我还不想急着离开病号房
I'm not anxious to get off the sick list.
另外 这是劳动工具 这儿流行这个
Besides, this is working kit. It's the fashion here.
你们当时连军官都干体力劳动吗？
The officers in your party did manual labour?
我想是的
I think you could call it that.
我可以列举出那个上校让我们做的每一点 他叫什么来着
I raised that very point with Colonel what's- his- name.
斋藤
Saito.
- 我认为他现在明白那样做是不对的了 - 是吗？
- I think he understands now. - Is that so?
是的 我必须说明 他看起来好像是那种很通情达理的类型
Yes. I must say he seems quite a reasonable type.
是这样啊 那我可得抓紧了
Well, I must be pushing on.
7点钟有个军官会议
There's an officer's meeting at 7.
- 把你的要求列个单子 - 是 长官
- Give me a list of your requirements. - Yes, sir.
我们会尽量满足
Anything we can do.
谢谢 长官
Thank you, sir.
- 这是为什么？ - 别介意
- What is it? - Never mind.
说说看
Go on, say it.
我可以想象出很多称呼Saito的词
I can think of a lot of things to call Saito...
…"通情达理" 倒是第一次听说
...but reasonable, that's a new one.
或许尼科尔森上校对这个词有不同的定义
Perhaps Col. Nicholson defines the word differently.
有其他补充的吗？
Any other points?
- 可以允许我说吗 长官？ - 詹宁斯？
- By your leave, sir? - Jennings?
有关逃跑委员会 我已经和舍尔斯司令官讨论过了…
About the escape committee. I've spoken with Cmd. Shears...
不会再有什么逃跑委员会了
There won't be any escape committee.
我不明白 长官 詹宁斯少尉有个计划
I don't understand, sir. Lt. Jennings has a plan.
是的 是的 我相信詹宁斯有个计划 但是 逃到哪里？
Yes, yes, I'm sure Jennings has a plan, but escape?
逃进雨林？ 那个Saito家伙说的是对的
Where? lnto this jungle? That fellow, Saito, is right.
这里是不需要铁丝网 逃进雨林只有1/100的生存可能
No need for barbed wire here. One chance in 1 00 of survival.
我认为象舍尔斯司令官 那样有经验的人会支持我的计划
I'm sure a man of Cmdr. Shears' experience will back me up on that.
我说过了逃跑成功的可能性是1/100
I'd say that the odds against a successful escape are 1 00 to one.
我可以插个嘴吗？
But may I add another word?
请
Please.
在这个战俘营的生存概率还要小
The odds against survival in this camp are even worse.
你已经看到了那些坟墓 他们是你在这里生存的真实几率
You've seen the graveyard. They're your real odds.
放弃逃走的希望…
To give up hope of escape...
…甚至不去考虑逃走 意味着接受死亡宣判
...to stop thinking about it means accepting a death sentence.
为什么到目前你还没有试着逃跑呢 司令官先生？
Why haven't you tried to escape, commander?
我在等候良机 等待正确的时间 和正确的伙伴
I'm biding my time. Waiting for the right moment, the right company.
我知道你的感受
I understand how you feel.
当然 作为一个被俘士兵 逃跑是他的天职
Of course, it's the duty of a captured soldier to attempt escape.
但是我和我的部下正处在一个奇怪的境地…
But my men and I are involved in a curious legal point...
而你并不知道这个
...of which you are unaware.
在新加坡 是指挥部命令我们投降的
In Singapore we were ordered to surrender by command headquarters.
请注意 是命令
Ordered, mind you.
所以 在我们这种情况下 逃跑就会违反战争法
Therefore, in our case, escape might well be an infraction of military law.
这真有意思 长官
Interesting point, sir.
对不起 长官 我不能同意你的观点
I'm sorry, sir, I didn't quite follow you.
你想不惜一切代价去遵守法律条文？
You intend to uphold the letter of the law, no matter what it costs?
没有了法律 指挥官先生 就不会有文明的存在
Without law, commander, there is no civilization.
这正是我的观点 在这里 没有文明
That's just my point. Here, there is no civilization.
那么 我们正好有机会在这里引进文明
Then we have the opportunity to introduce it.
我建议否决逃跑的议题
I suggest we drop the subject of escape.
还有什么要说的吗？
Is there anything else?
我想我们都清楚了
I think we're clear on the program.
我想从明天开始所有的事情都能顺利展开
I want everything to go off smoothly starting tomorrow morning.
并且 请各位记住:
And remember this:
必须要让我们的人感觉是我们在指挥他们…
Our men must always feel they are still commanded by us...
…而不是小日本
...and not by the Japanese.
这样 他们就会还是士兵 而不是奴隶
So long as they have that idea, they'll be soldiers and not slaves.
同意我的观点吗 指挥官先生？
Are you with me there, commander?
我希望他们还能是士兵 上校
I hope they can remain soldiers, colonel.
可我只是个奴隶
As for me, I'm just a slave.
一个还活着的奴隶
A living slave.
即使在美国人来说 他也是个古怪的家伙…
Queer bird. Even for an Ameri...
被囚禁得太久了 可怜的家伙
He's been in isolation too long, poor chap.
这就是脱离自己人的结果 对我们也是个教训
Cut off from his unit. It should be a lesson to all of us.
英军俘虏们！
English prisoners!
请注意我不是说"英军士兵"
Notice I do not say English soldiers.
当你们投降的那一刻起 你们就不是士兵了
From the moment you surrendered, you ceased to be soldiers.
你们要在五月12号前完成大桥
You will finish the bridge by the twelfth day of May.
你们会在小日本工程师的指导下工作
You will work under the direction of a Japanese engineer.
时间很短 所有人都得工作
Time is short. All men will work.
你们的军官会和你们一起工作
Your officers will work beside you.
投降就是你们的军官对你们的背叛
This is only just...
这就是对他们背叛你们的处罚
...for it is they who betrayed you by surrender.
羞辱你们就是要让羞辱他们
Your shame is their dishonour.
是他们告诉你们…
It is they who told you...
…好死不如赖活着
...better to live like a coolie then die like a hero.
是他们让你们来这里的 不是我
It is they who brought you here, not l.
所以 他们也要和你们一起干体力活
Therefore, they will join you in useful labour.
完毕
That is all.
军官俘虏们 拿好你们的工具
Officer prisoners, collect your tools.
布拉德利 归队
Bradley, back in your place.
我必须让你注意 Saito上校…
I must call your attention, Colonel Saito...
…在日内瓦公约的27条
...to Article 27 of the Geneva Convention.
" 交战国可以雇用战俘去做他们合适做的工作…
" Belligerents may employ prisoners of war...
…指挥官除外… "
...who are fit, other than officers..."
把书给我
Give me the book.
当然你能读懂英文吗？我有点怀疑
By all means. You read English, I take it?
- 你能读懂日文吗？ - 很遗憾 不会
- Do you read Japanese? - I'm sorry, no.
如果需要翻译 我想我可以安排
If it's a matter of translation, I'm sure it can be arranged.
你看 规则(Code)指出…
You see, the Code states that...
站着别动
Stand fast in the ranks.
你和我说"规则"？
You speak to me of Code?
你说的是什么"规则"？
What " Code"?
你说的是懦夫的"规则"！
The coward's code!
你知道什么是士兵的规则？
What do you know of the soldier's code?
你知道什么是武士道的规则？ 你什么都不知道！
Of bushido? Nothing!
你不配当指挥官！
You are unworthy of command!
如果你拒绝遵守文明世界的法规…
If you refuse to abide by the laws of the civilized world...
…那我们要考虑是否有义务去听从你的命令
...we must consider ourselves absolved from our duty to obey you.
我的军官不会去做体力劳动
My officers will not do manual labour.
我们走着瞧
We shall see.
所有战俘开始去工作
All enlisted prisoners to work.
军士长！ 带他们去工作
Sergeant Major! Take the men to work.
全体注意 拿起工具
Battalion, take up tools.
向左靠齐 向左转！
Move to the left in columnar route. Left turn!
"A" 队 齐步走
"A" Company, by the right, quick march.
向右看
Eyes right.
向前看
Eyes front.
齐步走 向右看
Quick march, eyes right.
" C" 队
" C" Company, by the right.
他在等什么？
What's he up to?
好像他不想有人看到
Looks like he doesn't want any witnesses.
现在 你是否会明白一些
Now, you will be reasonable.
命令你的指挥官去开始工作
You will order your officers to work.
不
No.
我数三下
I will count three.
如果数到第三下…
If by the third count...
…你和你的指挥官还没有去工作的话…
...you and your officers are not on the way to work...
…我就下令开枪
...l will give the order to fire.
他会这样做的
He's going to do it.
相信我 他确实想杀了他们
Believe me, he's really going to do it.
一
One.
我警告你 上校…
I warn you, Colonel....
二
Two.
等一等！
Stop!
Saito上校 我耳闻目睹了一切
Colonel Saito, I've seen and heard everything.
医院里的人也这样
So has every man in the hospital.
有太多的证人
They're too many witnesses.
你不能谎称这是集体逃跑 那些人很多连路都不能走
You can't call it a mass escape. Most of those men can't walk.
这就是你的士兵规则？ 屠杀手无寸铁的人？
Is this your soldier's code? Murdering unarmed men?
詹宁斯 你看 当个病号多好
You see, Jennings, there are advantages to being on the sick list.
我认为那老家伙勇气十足
I'll say this for the old man. He's got guts.
这样会死得更快
" Into the valley of death rode the 600."
怎么会那样 长官？
How's that, sir?
那种愚蠢的勇气
That kind of guts.
就像他们在1914一样…
Also the kind they had in 1 91 4...
…那时 军官们用拐杖来反抗
...when officers fought with only a swagger stick.
- 我明白你的意思 - 你一点也不明白我的意思
- I see what you mean. - You don't see what I mean at all.
那种勇气会让我们全部送命的
The kind of guts that can get us all killed.
对不起 长官 我也要和你一起逃跑
Excuse me, sir, I'd like to go along too.
我的胳膊差不多好了 长官 情况确实象你说的那样
Arm's almost healed, sir, really it is.
那他会同意吗？
What about him?
他并没有命令我们不准逃跑 他只是建议我们不逃跑
He didn't order us not to escape, he suggested.
听着 象你们上校那样人的建议就是命令
Listen, when a man like your colonel suggests something, it's an order.
又开始了
Here we go again.
Saito上校命令所有军官去惩戒室
Colonel Saito says all officers to punishment hut.
告诉他们去惩戒室
Tell them to go.
你留下
Not you.
过来
Come.
放了他！
Leave him alone!
他们要把他关进闷室
They're going to put him in the oven.
# For he's a jolly good fellow For he's a jolly good fellow
# For he's a jolly good fellow
# And so say all of us
# And so say all of us And so say all of us
# For he's a jolly good fellow For he's a jolly good fellow
# For he's a jolly good fellow
# And so say all of us
倒啦！
Timber!
一 二 三 四
One, two, three, four.
不行！
No, no, no!
松开！
Let go!
你想来见我？
You wish to see me?
3天来 我一直想见你
I've tried to see you for three days.
上校已经被关在闷室里…
It's about the colonel. He's been shut up in that hut...
我应该枪毙你
I could have you shot.
那些想逃跑的俘虏是你的手下
Those prisoners who tried to escape, they were in your charge.
对逃跑我毫不知情
I knew nothing about the escape.
那无关紧要
It does not matter.
那些逃跑的人值得尊敬
One must respect those who tried.
在逃亡和死亡的一瞬间…
For a brief moment, between escape and death...
他们又成了战士
...they were soldiers again.
但是试图从这里逃出去是愚蠢的
But it is insane to try and escape.
两个被枪打死 第三个被淹死
Two soldiers shot and the third drowned.
到头来又有什么好结果呢？
To what end?
只不过是逃避现实罢了
It was an escape from reality.
这是你的现实
There is your reality.
按计划 你们今天中午应该修到这里了
This shows the position work should have reached by noon today.
而实际上只到这里
And this shows the position of actual progress.
由于你们上校的愚顽不化 我们的进度远远落后了
Because of your colonel's stubbornness, we are far behind schedule.
还不止这些
That is not all.
战俘还蓄意破坏
Enlisted prisoners sabotaged the work.
是的 我看到的 我早就应该枪毙他们
Yes, I have seen it. I could have them all shot.
然后 谁替你造桥呢？
Then who would build your bridge?
另外 你认为那真的是蓄意破坏吗？
Besides, are you sure it's sabotage?
没有了自己的指挥官 他们的工作肯定不会做得太好
The men don't work well without their own officers.
我的指挥官会直接领导他们工作 你们的指挥官要和他们一块工作
My officers will direct them. Your officers will work beside them.
那要由尼科尔森来决定
That's for Nicholson to decide.
而且就像他说的那样 这样做是违背条约的
As he said, it's against the rules.
别和我谈什么条约
Do not speak to me of rules.
这是战争！
This is war!
并不是什么公平的游戏
This is not a game of cricket.
你的上校是个疯子
He's mad, your colonel...
完全是疯了
...quite mad.
请坐
Sit down, please.
我决定了 只让你一个人去看你们的上校
I have decided to allow you one visit to your colonel.
谢谢
Thank you.
告诉他 如果他的指挥官还不参加劳动的话…
Tell him that if his officers will not work...
我将不得不关闭医院…
...l'll be forced to close the hospital...
然后你的病人将替他们劳动
...and your patients will work in their place.
会死掉一些人 这全都要怪他
Many will die, and he will be responsible.
去和他讲你只有5分钟时间
Go and speak to him. You have five minutes.
医生要去看那老伙计了
Doc's going to see the old man.
长官…
Sir....
是科林普顿 长官
It's Clipton, sir.
我给你带来些东西
I brought you a few things.
- 我的部下怎么样了？ - 他们还好 长官
- How are the men? - Fine, sir, fine.
我们给您凑了点肉和一个椰子
We scraped together a little meat and a coconut.
军官们怎么样？
And the officers?
不太好 他们还在关禁闭
Not so good. They're still in detention.
詹宁斯上尉死了
And Lieutenant Jennings.... Jennings is dead.
- 什么？ - 在逃跑的时候被枪打死了
- What? - Killed, attempting to escape.
还有维佛下士和那个美国人
Also two others, Corporal Weaver and the American.
詹宁斯 真可怜 勇敢的小伙子
Jennings. Poor, brave lad.
我警告过他 对不对？
I warned him, didn't l, Clipton?
长官 我们时间不多了
Look, sir, we haven't much time.
我一边给你清理 一边说
I'm going to clean you up a little while I talk.
我有些事情要告诉你
I've got something to tell you.
我和Saito吵过了
I've just had a word with Saito.
那个家伙是我遇过的最差的指挥官
That man is the worst commanding officer I've ever come across.
他是个疯子 你说
Actually, I think he's mad. Carry on.
讹诈！
Blackmail!
我知道 长官 但他是认真的
I know, sir, but he means it. I'm sure he does.
很简单 这是个关于面子的问题 但他是不会屈服的
It's a question of face, pure and simple. And he can't give in.
但那仍然是讹诈
It's still blackmail.
长官 你是撑不过他的
Sir, you can't stand much more of this.
我们那些军官被憋在那个闷室里也不是办法
Wouldn't the officers be better off working than suffocating in that hole?
我们的士兵在尽量地拖延工期
The men are doing a wonderful job. They're going as slow as they dare.
但是Saito在削减他们的食物配额…
But Saito's cut their food rations...
并且一旦他让病人去工作…
...and if he makes the sick men work....
很显然就会死很多人
Well, they're going to die. That's all there is to it.
是的 科林普顿 我很清楚
Yes, Clipton, I understand. Truly.
但是你看到了吗？这关乎原则
But don't you see? It's a matter of principle.
如果我们现在屈服了 就会无休无止 不行
If we give in now, there'll be no end to it. No.
长官 我们陷在雨林里 远离文明
Sir, we're lost in the jungle, a thousand miles from anywhere.
我们是在一个为了达到自己目的可以不择手段的家伙的统治下 更别说原则了！
We're under a man who'll stop at nothing to get his way. Principle!
没有人会知道这儿发生了什么 也不会有人关心
No one will ever know or care what happens to us.
退一步吧 长官 求求你了！
Give in, sir. Please!
我不会动摇的
I'm adamant.
我不会让我的军官去象一个小工一样干苦力
I will not have an officer from my battalion working as a coolie.
- 时间到 - 好的
- Time. - All right.
谢谢关心我的人
Please thank those concerned.
医院里的每个人都献了一片肉
Everybody in the hospital contributed one piece.
雷诺兹偷了个椰子
Reynolds stole the coconut.
我们还会给你带来食物的
We'll be able to get you food sometimes.
我们已经贿赂了一个看管你的守卫
We've bribed one of your guards.
再见 长官 祝好运
Goodbye, sir. And good luck.
多谢
Many thanks.
你说那个美国人被打死了？
Did you say that American was killed?
是的 长官 被枪打倒后淹死了
Yes, sir. Shot and drowned.
计划逃跑真是个愚蠢的念头
It's insane to plan escapes.
3人被杀 结果怎么样呢？
Three men killed, and to what end?
时间到！
Time!
我们在这里一定能胜利
Here is where we must win through.
医生看着我们并摇摇头 什么意思
Doc just looked at us and shook his head. Whatever that means.
只有一个意思 上校不会屈服
Means only one thing, the colonel won't give in.
怎么样？
Well?
是这样的
It's like this.
尼科尔森上校不准备向武力屈服
Colonel Nicholson won't give in to force.
这是个原则的问题
It's a question of principle.
作为医疗官 我抗议对他的折磨
As medical officer, I protest the way he's being treated.
他还能活着 真是奇迹
It's a wonder he's still alive.
如果发生悲剧 那和谋杀是一样的
Should a tragedy occur, it would be tantamount to murder.
要怪就怪他
He is responsible.
不是我
Not l.
你病了？
You sick?
他们都疯了吗？
Are they both mad?
或者我也要发疯了？
Or am I going mad?
太阳也疯了？
Or is it the sun?
立正！
Attention!
全体立正
Battalion, attention.
英军俘虏们
English prisoners.
让我们问一个问题…
Let us ask the question...
…为什么大桥进展迟缓？
...why does the bridge not progress?
你们知道为什么 因为你们的指挥官是懒惰的！
You know why, because your officers are lazy!
他们认为自己高人一等 而不愿和你们分担
They think themselves too good to share your burden.
这是不公平的
This is not just.
所以 你们工作起来也不愉快
Therefore, you are not happy in your work.
所以 大桥也没有什么进展
Therefore, the bridge does not progress.
但是还有一个原因
But there is another cause.
我不避讳事实
I do not hide the truth.
我很惭愧…
With deep shame and regret...
…我承认也是由于我们的一个小日本狗屎
...l admit to you the failure...
…的无能
...of a member of the Japanese staff.
我是指 Miura上尉
I refer to Lieutenant Miura.
他是一个很差的工程师
He is a bad engineer.
他的指挥毫不称职
He is unworthy of command.
所以 我把他撤换了
Therefore, I have removed him from his post.
明天 我们重新开始
Tomorrow we begin again.
我会亲自指挥
I shall be in personal command.
今天 我们休息
Today we rest.
只有工作而没有娱乐会很不爽的！
All work and no play make Jack a dull boy!
为了你们明天努力工作…
As token of regard for your efforts in the future...
…我给你们每个人一份礼物
...l give presents to you all.
工作愉快
Let us be happy in our work.
解散
Company, dismissed.
全体解散
Battalion, dismissed.
嘿 看看
Hey, take a look at this.
红十字！ 他把我们的…
Red Cross! He's given us our...
嘿 他把我方的红十字包裹发给我们
Hey, he's given us our own Red Cross parcels.
"明天重新开始"
"Tomorrow we begin again."
嘿 哈里 看！
Hey, Harry, look!
他们要把老伙计放出来了
They're letting the old man out.
看来 他们要再毒打他一顿
Most likely going to give him another pasting.
晚上好 上校
Good evening, colonel.
愿意过来坐一坐吗？
Do you mind sitting over here?
我晚饭还没有吃
I am having rather a late supper.
英国咸牛肉
English corned beef.
不用 谢谢
No, thank you.
产自苏格兰
Produce of Scotland.
我宁愿它是日本米酒
I prefer it to sake.
我在伦敦呆了3年
I spent three years in London, you know.
我在伦敦工艺学校学习
I studied at the London Polytechnic.
敬你！
Cheers!
抱歉
Sorry.
下次？
Later, perhaps?
也许
Perhaps.
我不是一个好的艺术家
I was not a good artist.
我爸爸不赞成我搞艺术
My father disapproved.
他觉得我应该在军队发展
He felt I belonged in the army.
所以我放弃了艺术 改学工程
So I changed from art to engineering.
我必须告诉你 Saito上校
I must tell you, Colonel Saito.
我要将你的行为写一份完整的报告
I intend to make a full report of your activities.
我不认为你理解我的处境
I do not think you quite realize my position.
- 我必须执行给我的命令 - 噢 当然
- I must carry out my orders. - Oh, quite, quite.
我必须在5月12号之前完成大桥
My orders are to complete the bridge by the 1 2th day of May.
- 我只有12个星期多一点 - 是的
- I have only 1 2 weeks more. - No doubt.
所以 我必须启用我手上的任何一个人
Therefore, I am compelled to use all available personnel.
军官不行 除非是管理工作
No officers, except for administration.
但是在这条铁路线上 所有的军官都在工作
But officers are working along the entire railway.
你清楚 我也清楚
You know it. I know it.
其他地方的军官我不管
I'm not responsible for other officers.
从我个人来讲 我很震惊
Personally, I'm appalled.
别激动
Let's not get excited.
来枝雪茄吗？
Will you have a cigar?
不 谢谢
No. Thank you.
当我说所有的指挥官都要劳动的时候…
When I said all officers must work...
…事实上是指少尉至上校阶级之各指挥官 并没有包括你
...naturally, I never meant you, the commanding officer.
我的命令只适用于下级军官…
My orders were only intended for officers below...
任何军官都不能做苦力劳动
No officers will do manual labour.
拜托！ 我是要说:
Please! I was about to say:
我通盘考虑过了
I've thought the matter over and have decided...
…我要让他们大部分做管理工作
...to put majors and above on administrative duties...
…只有很低级的军官去劳动
...leaving only junior officers to work.
不行 公约关于这个的规定很清楚
No. The Convention's quite clear on that point.
你知道如果大桥不能准时建成 我会怎样？
Do you know what will happen to me if the bridge is not ready in time?
一点也不知道
I haven't the foggiest.
我必须自杀
I'd have to kill myself.
如果你是我 你会怎样？
What would you do if you were me?
如果我是你…
I suppose if I were you...
…我想我会自杀
...l'd have to kill myself.
敬你
Cheers.
我警告你 上校…
I warn you, colonel...
…在我死之前 其他的人都得死
...if I am to die, others will die before me.
你明白了吗？
Do you understand?
科林普顿并没有这么说
Clipton did mention that.
但那样也不能解决你的问题
That won't solve your problem.
我想我们可以达成一个解决办法
I'm sure we can arrive at a solution.
请坐
Please sit down.
请你告诉我 上校…
Now. Tell me, colonel...
你认为军人的天职是服从命令吗？
...do you agree that the first job of an officer is command?
- 当然 - 好的
- Of course. - Good.
现在
Now.
我们来看看你的大桥
Take this bridge of yours.
真是一个巨大的工程
It's quite an enormous undertaking.
坦率地说 我怀疑你的那个叫什么来着的上尉…
Frankly, I doubt whether your Lieutenant what's- his- name...
三浦
Miura.
能胜任这样的工作
...is capable of tackling a job of such importance.
另外 我有些军官 比如里夫和休斯…
On the other hand, I have officers, Reeves and Hughes for instance...
…他们在印度到处修桥
...who have built bridges all over lndia.
人们都尊敬他们
The men respect them.
尊重对一个军官来说是很重要的
It's essential for an officer to have that respect.
如果没有尊重 则不能服众
If it's gone, he ceases to command.
然后会怎么样？ 部下漫无纪律 指挥混乱
What then? Demoralization and chaos.
如果让这种情况发生 那么我就是个非常不称职的指挥官
A poor commander I would be if I allowed that to happen.
也许你忘记了 修建大桥是由我来指挥的
Perhaps you are not aware that the bridge is now under my command.
真的吗？ 你对进度满意吗？
Really? And may I ask, are you satisfied with the work?
- 很不满意！ - 你证明了我的观点
- I am not! - You've proved my point.
我痛恨英国人！
I hate the British!
你们被打败了 还不知羞耻
You are defeated but you have no shame.
你们很顽固 但没有什么值得自豪的
You are stubborn but have no pride.
你们会忍耐 但你们没有勇气
You endure but you have no courage.
我痛恨英国人！
I hate the British!
这样不能解决任何问题
Pointless, going on like this.
站着！
Stay there!
暂停！
Stand down. Stand down!
全体立正！
Battalion, attention!
全体 稍息
Battalion, stand at ease.
请…
Please....
你知道今天是什么日子吗 上校？
Do you know what is the date today, colonel?
我已经不会记数了
I've lost count.
这是我们1905年
It's the anniversary of our great victory...
大胜俄国人的纪念日…
...over Russia in 1 905.
整个东亚都在庆祝这个日子
Throughout East Asia we are celebrating this date.
趁着这个伟大的日子…
In honour of this occasion...
…我给你的部下放了一天假
...l have given your troops a day of rest.
多谢
Many thanks.
我要宣布一个特赦
I am declaring a general amnesty.
你和你的军官可以回到你们的住处
You and your officers may return to your quarters.
作为这个特赦的一部分…
As part of this amnesty...
…军官不需要做体力劳动了
...it will not be necessary for officers to do manual labour.
他做到了！
He's done it!
应该给某些人发勋章
Somebody deserves a medal, sir.
你的手下有多少人？
How many men in your party?
我不是很清楚 长官
I don't really know, sir.
- 你不清楚？ - 通常有12个人
- You don't know? - Twelve, usually.
今早有一个生病了 长官
One of the men took sick this morning, sir.
有三四个人把他抬到医院去了
It took three or four to help him to the hospital.
嗯 他病得很厉害 长官
And... He took terrible sick, sir.
一个下士必须清楚他管辖多少人
A corporal should know how many men he has under him.
是 长官
Oh, yes, sir.
你的面部神经有问题吗？ 否则 不要那样做鬼脸
Have you a nervous affliction? Stop making those faces.
也许你认为很有趣 但不要那样做鬼脸
It may be funny to you, but it's not military behaviour.
没有问题 长官
No, sir.
我们必须停止这些作假行为
We must put a stop to these demonstrations.
- 我说 里夫？ - 什么 长官？
- I say, Reeves? - Yes, sir?
以前在这类河上修建过大桥吗？
Ever built a bridge over a stream like the Kwai?
是的 长官 我们在马德拉斯和孟加拉修的桥有半数是这类的
Yes, sir, half a dozen of them in Madras, Bengal....
如果这是你负责修建的大桥…
If this were your bridge...
你会怎样来做…？
...how would you get it under way?
怎样来做？
Get it under way, sir?
首先 我不会把它修在这里
First of all, I wouldn't build it here.
噢 为什么？
Oh, why not?
我可以说…
I was trying to tell you...
…小日本不可能再找到比这里糟糕的地点了
...the Japanese couldn't have picked a worse location.
你看到这些桥桩了吗？
You see those piles?
他们正在下沉
They're sinking.
他们要经常受到压力 而他们不可能支撑的住
We could drive those logs forever and they wouldn't hold.
那你会在哪里建桥？
Where would you build it?
下游较远一点的地方 长官 在那些河道狭窄的地方跨越河流
Further downstream, sir. Across those narrows.
这样两岸都会有坚实的岩床
Then we'd have solid bedrock on both banks.
休斯 如果是你负责修建大桥 你会怎么安排人手？
Hughes, if this were your bridge, how would you use the men?
绝对不是现在这样子 正如你看到的 太混乱了
Not the way they're doing it. It's chaos, as you can see.
作业互不协调
Uncoordinated activity.
相互没有配合
No teamwork.
很多组的工作相互制约
Some parties are working against each other.
是的
Yes.
我说 先生们 我们手上有个难题
I say, gentlemen, we have a problem on our hands.
感谢小日本所赐 我们在指挥一群乌合之众
Thanks to the Japanese, we command a rabble.
没有秩序 没有原则
There's no order, no discipline.
- 我们的任务是要重组军队 - 是的 长官
- Our task is to rebuild the battalion. - Yes, sir.
那并不容易
Which isn't going to be easy.
幸运的是 我们手上有个对象 那座大桥
Fortunately, we have the means at hand. The bridge.
- 那座大桥 长官？ - 是的 那座大桥
- The bridge, sir? - The bridge.
我们要展示我们西方的效率 给他们上一课 让他们出出丑
We'll teach them a lesson in Western efficiency that'll put them to shame.
展示我们英军士兵的能力
Show what a British soldier is capable of.
是的 长官 我明白你的意思
Yes. I see your point, sir.
我知道这儿环境很艰苦…
I know how difficult it's going to be here...
…找不到合手的东西
...where you can't find what you need.
- 这是一个挑战 - 请原谅 长官
- There's the challenge. - I beg your pardon, sir.
你真的要给他们修一座大桥？
You really want them to build the bridge?
你们平时可不是这么迟钝的
You're not usually so slow in the uptake.
我知道我们的战士 必须让他们有活干
I know our men. You've got to keep them occupied.
如果他们没有事干 我们就找一些给他们做
If there weren't any work, we'd invent some.
- 我们会的 长官 - 我们很幸运
- That we would, sir. - So we're lucky.
但是我们还要把它造好
But it's going to be a proper bridge.
我还知道我们的战士
Here again I know the men.
他们需要在工作中寻找自豪感
It's essential that they take pride in their job.
- 对不对 各位？ - 是的 长官
- Right, men? - Yes, sir.
里夫 你是这里的关键人员 你在这里要充当一个工程师
Reeves, you're the key man here as engineer.
告诉我你需要的 我们会尽量去满足 我们能干好吗？
Tell me what you want and we'll get it. Can we make a go of it?
- 我们会干的很漂亮的 长官 - 很好
- We'll do out best, sir. - Fine.
我们必须先制定计划…
We must draw up our plans...
…然后和Saito开个会议…
...then arrange a conference with Saito...
…然后纠正他的错误
...and set him straight.
那些全是程序上的事情
That takes care of all the procedural matters.
噢 是的
Oh, yes.
下面我要说的可能相关的人员会不高兴
The next point is unpleasant for all concerned, I'm afraid.
我不得不说 大桥的选址是草率的…
Sorry to say, the position of the bridge was fixed hastily...
…嗯 或者说是错误的
...and, I have to add, incorrectly.
错误的？
Incorrectly?
很不幸 是的
Unfortunately, yes.
我们的技术人员研究了你们选的地点…
Our engineer has made a study of the site...
…认为河床太软
...and decided that the river bottom there is too soft.
太软？
Too soft?
全是泥浆！ 所有的工作都是无用工
Mud! All the work has been useless.
- 里夫 请你继续 - 是的 长官
- Reeves, will you carry on? - Yes, sir.
桥墩的受力会把它们压到水面以下的
Those piles of yours could be hammered below water level before they'd hold.
当第一列火车通过的时候 大桥就会倒塌
It would collapse under the first train.
这是压力和泥土形变的图表 单位是吨/平方英寸
The pressure and soil resistance figures in tons per square inch.
里夫 在你深入介绍之前… 上校 我们可以来杯茶吗？
Reeves, before you get too involved.... Colonel, could we have a cup of tea?
我认为大家都同意了 为了避免灾难…
I take it we all agree that if we're to avoid disaster...
…我们必须在下游400码的地方 在里夫挑选的地址上建一座新桥
...we build a new bridge, at the site picked by Reeves, 400 yards downstream.
现在我们来看下一个问题
Let's proceed to the next point.
我要改变他们的劳动强度
I decided to alter the work quota of our men.
- 改变劳动强度？ - 我要增加他们的劳动强度
- Alter? - I've increased it.
从挖土15码改成2码
From 1 .5 yards of earth moved to two.
你肯定会赞同这个决定
I'm sure it will meet with your approval.
休斯 你来详细介绍一下
Hughes has all the facts. Would you take over?
我仔细研究了一下整个工程
I've done a time study of the entire project.
我认为 作业分配是错误的
You see, the available forces have been badly distributed.
我们应该修改作业分配
I'd urge we revise the organization of the working parties.
稍等一下 上校 我们边吃边谈可能会节约时间
Just a moment. Colonel, it would save time if we could work during dinner.
我们可以有晚饭吃的吧？
Would it be possible to have dinner?
当然
Of course.
- 继续 - 是 长官
- Carry on. - Yes, sir.
如果增加班组 细化分工…
If we increase the squads and specialize their functions...
…那么 每天的工作量会增加30%
...l'm certain the total daily output can be increased by 30?0 .
现在 Saito 上校 我还有一点补充…
Now, Colonel Saito, I have one more point....
现在 还有一项决定刻不容缓
Now, there's another important decision that can't be postponed.
当英军士兵在修桥的时候…
As the British will work on the bridge...
…修建铁路的人手就少了
...only a few will be available for railway work.
你必须用你的人来支援铁路的修建…
I must ask you to lend us some of your men to reinforce the railway gang...
…那样 铺轨的工作也能尽快的完成
...so the final stretch of track can be completed as quickly as possible.
我已经下令了
I have already given the order.
我们也必须改变你们的工作强度
We must fix the daily work quota for your men.
我曾想过定为每天15码 这样不会太过疲劳…
I thought to set it at 1 .5 yards so as not to overtire them...
…但是和我们一样是不是更好一些？
...but isn't it best to be the same as ours?
这样也会形成良性竞争
That would also create a healthy competitive spirit.
我已经下令了
I have already given the order.
我们会尽善尽美的 对不对 休斯？
We'll try to surpass that, won't we, Hughes?
我想今晚的议程就到这里
I think that completes the agenda for tonight.
谢谢你的关注 Saito上校
Thank you, Colonel Saito, for your kind attention.
还有问题吗？
Are there any other questions?
我有一个问题
One question.
你能在期限内完成大桥吗？
Can you finish the bridge in time?
坦率地讲 看起来是不可能的
Frankly, the consensus of opinion is that it's impossible.
当然我们要试一试
But we'll certainly give it a go.
别忘了 我们因为分歧而浪费了一个月…
Don't forget we wasted a month through an unfortunate disagreement...
…当然那不是我的错
...for which I was not to blame.
还有什么问题吗？
Is there anything else?
没有了
No.
谢谢 会议结束
Thank you. The meeting is closed.
- 晚安 - 晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
我希望这些小日本会感激我们所做的
I hope these Japanese appreciate what we're doing for them.
虽然现在我还没有感觉到这一点
For now I'm not concerned with their appreciation.
- 晚安 科林普顿 - 晚安 长官
- Good night, Clipton. - Good night, sir.
另外 我想告诉你…
By the way, I meant to tell you...
…这里有一些树比较象榆树
...there are trees here similar to elm.
伦敦桥的榆树桩已经支撑了600年了
And the elm piles of London Bridge lasted 600 years.
- 600年 里夫？ - 是的 长官
- Six hundred years, Reeves? - Yes, sir.
600年
Six hundred years.
真是奇迹
That would be quite something.
我在找一个美国人 他叫 舍尔斯
I'm looking for an American named Commander Shears.
- 在海滩上 - 谢谢
- Yes, down on the beach. - Oh, thank you very much.
吻一下！
Kiss!
那么多人
Too many eyes.
你给了我药粉 药片 沐浴 注射 灌肠…
You give me powders, pills, baths, injections, enemas....
其实我只需要爱
All I need is love.
是的 你只需要爱
It's true. All you really need is love.
为什么你这么肯定你想病休？
Why are you so sure you'll get a medical discharge?
因为我内心里一直是老百姓 宝贝
Because I'm a civilian at heart, lover.
而且我一直是性情中人
And I always follow my heart.
吻一下
Kiss.
怎么会那样 司令官？
How's that, commander?
不要叫我司令官
Don't call me commander.
太不浪漫了
It's unromantic.
你自己也是个军官
You're an officer yourself.
你会喜欢我叫你宝贝上尉吗？
How'd you like it if I called you Lieutenant Lover?
让我们用平民的称呼吧 就叫我"先生"吧
Let's be democratic. Just call me "sir."
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
厚颜无耻
Brass ahoy.
他来找你
He wants you. He's all yours.
- 我要去游泳了 - 别走！
- I'm going for a swim. - Don't leave me!
- 舍尔斯 司令官？ - 是的
- Commander Shears? - Yes.
我叫 华登
My name's Warden.
- 你好 - 对不起 打扰了…
- How do you do? - Sorry to intrude...
没事 少校 我习惯了
That's okay, major. I'm used to it.
来点马丁尼酒吗？
Like a martini?
谢谢 不用了
That's very kind. I think not.
介意我来一点吗？
Mind if I have one?
哪里搞来的？
How did you get that?
有医院就有酒精
Where there's a hospital, there's alcohol.
噢 那当然
Yes, of course. Jolly good.
嗯 我尽量简洁一些
Well, I'll be as brief as possible.
我隶属于316部队 那是个比较古怪的部门
I belong to a rather rum group called Force 31 6.
我们的总部在布坦尼可公园 (Botanical Gardens(植物园))
Our headquarters is in the Botanical Gardens.
- 保护稀有植物不被敌人破坏？ - 当然不是
- Protecting rare plants from the enemy? - Not quite.
- 你当真不来一点？ - 不 谢谢
- Sure you won't have one? - No, thanks.
我们对你工作过的铁路很感兴趣
We have an interest in that railway you worked on.
你可以给我们很多有价值的情报
You could give us no end of valuable information.
嗯 我已经离开那地方已经很多天了…
Well, I'm leaving for the States in a few days...
…而且我把所知的都告诉你们了
...and I told your people everything I know.
但是你可以用一种更特殊的方式来帮助我们
But you could help us in a rather special sense.
我知道有点强人所难 但是你能否出来去见一下我们？
I know it's a terrible imposition, but could you possibly come out and see us?
如果你想让我再重复报告一遍的话
If you want to go over the whole thing again.
太好了 路易斯阁下会感激不尽的
Very kind. Lord Louis'll be grateful.
- 谁？ - 蒙巴顿
- Who? - Mountbatten.
我们是他的部下
We're one of his special pigeons.
那么今晚怎么样？ 8点我会派一辆车来
Shall we say this evening, then? About 8. I'll send a car.
今晚？ 不行
This evening? Out of the question.
你明早怎么样？ 10点？
Tomorrow morning then? About 1 0?
- 好 就10点 - 多谢
- Okay, 1 0:00. - Thanks very much.
- 再见 - 再见
- Cheerio. - Cheerio.
祝你好运
Good luck.
谢谢
Thanks.
你很抱歉 你今晚要让我空等了
You're sorry, but you're going to stand me up tonight.
大错特错
You couldn't be more wrong.
敬礼！
General salute!
举枪致敬！
Present arms!
- 可以看你的通行证吗？ - 好的
- May I see your pass, please? - Oh, yes.
华登少校的办公室在路的尽头
Major Warden's bungalow is at the end of the path.
干得好 Jenkins 干得好！
Good show, Jenkins. Good show!
快 汤姆森用你的匕首
Come along, Thomson. Use your knife, man.
站起来！快去指定地点
On your feet! Away to the debriefing room.
快 快点！
Come on, move yourselves! Move quickly!
动作太笨了 乔依斯
Very clumsy, Joyce, very clumsy.
要立即用匕首捅 乔依斯
Always use your knife immediately, Joyce.
你看 他占了主动
You see, he's gained the initiative.
停下！ 对不起 长官
Wait a minute! I'm terribly sorry, sir.
- 你对不起？ - 是的
- You're sorry? - So am l.
- 我以为你是敌人 - 我是美国人 如果你是指这个的话
- I thought you were the enemy. - I'm American, if that's what you mean.
- 就这样 乔依斯 - 是 长官 对不起 长官
- That'll be all, Joyce. - Yes, sir. Sorry, sir.
- 我能做什么？ - 我要找华登上校
- What can I do for you? - I'm going to see Major Warden.
我来带路 他现在应该快下课了
I'll show you the way. He'll finish his lecture any moment now.
- 他现在下课了 - 这么大的声音
- That's the end of his lecture. - Thunderous ovation.
他认为训练越接近实战越好
He believes in keeping our training as close to real life as possible.
- 华登少校 - 嗯？
- Major Warden, sir? - Yes?
很高兴见到你
Good of you to come.
- 他们待你还好吧？ - 确实是的
- They took care of you? - They certainly have.
谢谢你 跟我来
Thank you, staff. Well, come along, then.
格林上校要见你
Col. Green is looking forward to meeting you.
- 这个地方还不错吧？ - 我不知道这里还是一所军事学校
- Fascinating place, isn't it? - Didn't know it was a commando school.
我们尽量不用这种称呼 那样会制造紧张空气
We're trying to discourage the use of that word. Such a melodramatic air.
你在这里干什么？
What do you do here?
爆破 摧毁一类的事情
Sabotage, demolition, that line of country.
我们使用 PE 塑胶炸药 很不错的东西
We're using P.E., plastic explosives. It's wonderful.
刚才那个爆炸的炸药只有这个一半大
That pop was made with a lump half this size.
只要硝化甘油炸药的一半 而威力却有两倍
It's twice as powerful as gelignite at half the weight.
没引爆的情况下是很安全的
It's quite harmless until it's detonated.
谢谢你的介绍
Thanks for telling me.
它完全防水 而且可塑性很好
It's completely waterproof and actually plastic.
看到吗？你可以用它来做你想用它做的事情
See? You can do what you like with it.
这是我的办公室
This is my place.
这里
Go ahead.
喔 渴死了 我要来杯茶
Oh, I'm dying for a cup of tea.
- 你也来一杯？ - 不 谢谢
- Would you care for one? - No, thanks.
- 来杯酒？ - 不 谢谢
- A drink? - No, thank you.
- 给我来壶茶 彼得 - 是的 长官
- Pot of tea for one, please, Peter. - Very good, sir.
这个你也看得懂？
Do you read this?
战前 我在剑桥教东方语言
I taught Oriental languages at Cambridge before the war.
我还没有祝贺你的成功逃亡呢 干得好！
I never congratulated you on your escape. Good show!
如果你的海上救援飞机没有看到我 我也不会呆在这里
If your sea rescue plane hadn't spotted me, I wouldn't be here.
是的 我想不会
No, I suppose not.
你愿意再来看看你逃出来的地方吗？
Would you like to see where you were?
好的
All right.
我们的情报很有限 主要来源于你的报告
Our information's scanty. It's based on your report.
我们认为战俘营在这里
We think the camp's here.
你们是否有尼科尔森上校的消息？
Do your people have any idea what happened to Col. Nicholson?
他很勇敢 要枪毙他时 他也不眨一下眼睛
He had guts. They were about to shoot him and he didn't bat an eye.
当你要被枪毙的时候 你本来就什么也不能做
If you're about to be shot there's not much you can do.
这里是桂河 这里是你求助的村子
Here is the river Kwai, and here's the village where you were helped.
这里是铁路
Here is the railway.
你肯定非常熟悉这一带
You must be fairly familiar with this area.
不 大部分时间我脑袋里只是一片空白
No, I was out of my head half the time.
铁路从新加坡开始 经过马来西亚…
The railway starts down here in Singapore. Malaya...
…曼谷 仰光 他们想一直贯通到印度
...Bangkok, Rangoon. Their idea is to drive on through, into lndia.
- 我是在哪里被救起的？ - 在这里附近
- Where was I picked up? - Oh, about here.
日军想在五月中旬贯通曼谷和仰光
The Japanese aim to open the Bangkok-  Rangoon section by the middle of May.
我们必须阻止他们
We'll try to prevent them.
太远了 轰炸机飞不到这里
It's too far for bombers to carry a load.
我们必须用地面部队把它摧毁
We'll have to go smash it on the ground.
- 那你想怎么办？ - 空降之后 徒步到那里
- How? - Parachute drop, then march.
带着爆破装置穿过雨林吗？
With demolition equipment through that jungle?
我们的主要问题是对那里一无所知
Our chief problem is lack of firsthand knowledge.
我们没有人到过哪里
You see, none of us have ever been there.
- 我其实不想让你失望 但是… - 那很有趣
- I don't want to discourage... - It should be interesting.
格林上校把桂河大桥交给我了 我要带一队人去炸掉它
Col. Green's given me the Kwai bridge. I'm taking a team in to blow it up.
你真幸运
Lucky you.
你真的不想来点茶？
Sure you won't have tea?
不 谢谢 我不想失礼 但是我在2点钟要和一个漂亮的姑娘约会
No, thanks. I don't want to be rude, but I've got a date at 2.
- 如果还有问题的话… - 很抱歉 是的
- If there are any questions.... - Of course, I'm sorry.
嗯 只有一个问题
Well, there is only one question, actually.
你觉得再去哪里一趟怎么样？
How would you feel about going back?
什么？
Come again?
在某种情况下 有点儿…
Under the circumstances it's a bit much...
…但是你是我们完成这个任务的关键
...but you have a unique knowledge for our purpose.
我们很希望你能和我们一起去
We'd love to have you with us.
这就是你找我来这里的原因？
That's why you brought me here?
来请我再去哪里一趟？
To ask me this?
嗯 坦率的说 是的
Well, frankly, yes.
我才从那里逃出来
I just got out of there.
我能从那里逃出来 简直是个奇迹 而你现在却让我再回去！ 真荒唐！
My escape was a miracle. Now you want me to go back! Ridiculous!
我知道这很令人为难…
This is embarrassing...
我不属于你们的部队 我隶属于美国海军
I don't belong to you. I belong to the American Navy.
事实上 格林上校和你的部队讨论过这件事
Actually, Col. Green has taken the matter up with your people.
- 和我的部队？ - 你的海军把你转借给我们
- With my people? - Your Navy's turned you over to us.
昨天早上 从太平洋舰队指挥部来了一个命令…
A signal arrived yesterday morning from the Pacific...
确认把你暂借给316部队
...authorizing your temporary transfer of duty to Force 31 6.
- 他们不能这样做！ - 恐怕他们不这样认为
- They can't do this! - I'm afraid they have.
很遗憾告诉你这个消息
It was hard to break it to you.
但是他们不能这样对我 海军搞错了！
But they can't do this to me. I mean it. My Navy's made a mistake!
你看 我不是海军司令官 我甚至不是一名军官
Look. I'm not a Navy commander. I'm not even an officer.
整个事情都不是真的 我只是一个擦炮筒的普通士兵
The whole thing's a fake. I'm just an ordinary swab jockey, second class.
当休斯顿号沉没的时候 我和一名真正的司令官上岸
When the Houston sunk, I made it ashore with a real commander.
我们碰上了日军巡逻队 他被打死了
We ran into a Japanese patrol. He was killed.
我认为只是时间问题 直到我…
I figured it was just a matter of time till l...
所以你和死人换了服装
So you changed uniforms with a dead man.
我认为在战俘营中军官会受到较好的待遇
I thought officers would get better treatment in prison camps.
但是我遇到的Saito 他命令指挥官和其他人一起劳动
But with Saito, the officers worked along with the rest.
总是有意想不到的事情 对不对？
There's always the unexpected, isn't there?
我已经有点习惯当司令官了…
I kind of got used to being a commander...
…所以当我来到医院的时候…
...so when I arrived at the hospital...
…我看了一下普通战士的病房和指挥官的病房…
...l took a look at the enlisted men's ward and then the officer's ward...
…然后我对自己说 "就继续冒充一些时间吧"
...and I said to myself, " Let's let it ride along for a while."
军官还真有优待
There were certain advantages.
我在海滩上就看到一个
I saw one of them on the beach.
这就是整个故事
That's the whole story.
问题是 你不能用我 你需要的是一名指挥官…
The point is, you can't use me. You want an officer...
…一个并不存在的美军司令官舍尔斯
...an American Commander Shears who doesn't exist.
当海军发现了真相 他们会说:
When the Navy learns the truth, they'll say:
"由于假扮指挥官 把他遣送回家"
"Ship him home for impersonating an officer."
- 一旦结果是那样 我就成功了 - 你就怎样？
- Once that happens, I've got it made. - Got it what?
成功了！ 我现在想喝点酒
Made! I'd like that drink now.
我想申请病退
I'll apply for a medical discharge.
我会说假装指挥官是由于在森林中得了神经病
I'll say I impersonated an officer because I went crazy in the jungle.
甚至 有时我觉得我是海尔森海军舰队司令
I'm getting worse. Sometimes I think I'm Admiral Halsey.
很聪明的计划
It's quite a clever plan.
不仅仅是是聪明的计划 而且是简单安全的
Not only clever, it's foolproof.
如果海军发现了我的真实身份
If my Navy finds out who I am...
那份命令就是一张废纸
...those orders won't be worth the paper they're written on.
这是你的照片吗？
Isn't this your photograph?
- 从哪里搞到的？ - 由于你的部队不能确认你的身份…
- Where did you get this? - It took some doing...
…就费了些事
...since your people couldn't identify you.
最后你的太平洋舰队发了一份你的服役档案过来
Finally your C- in- C Pacific sent us a copy of your service record.
照片和指纹 你愿意看看吗？
The photograph, fingerprints. Would you care to have a look?
我们知道你的真实身份已经有一个星期了
You see, we've known about your actual rank for nearly a week.
你的海军处在一个两难的境地
Your Navy's in an awkward position.
一方面你是个英雄…
In one sense you're a hero...
…成功逃出雨林
...for making an escape from the jungle.
同时 因为你假扮指挥官
At the same time, they can't bring you home...
他们又不好把你送回家 然后颁发一枚海军十字勋章给你
...and give you the Navy Cross for impersonating an officer.
我想因此他们很乐意把你转交给我们
I suppose that's why they were happy to hand you over.
你明白了吗？
You see?
棘手的问题
Hot potato.
说到你的军阶
As far as your rank is concerned...
在316部队 我们并不在意那个
...we're fairly informal about that in Force 31 6.
你可以假装你是少校
You'd have the simulated rank of major.
假装上校 那意味着…
A simulated major. That figures.
嗯…
Well....
我最好是志愿参加
As long as I'm hooked, I might as well volunteer.
很好！
Good show!
格林上校 长官
Oh, Colonel Green, sir.
这是舍尔斯上校 他志愿帮助我们炸掉那座桥
This is Major Shears. He volunteered to go and help me blow up the bridge.
真的？
Really?
很好！
Good show!
太好了 上校！
Jolly good show, major!
去医务室吧 这只脚感染了
Get up to sick bay. This foot's infected.
上校会以为我在装病
Colonel might think I'm malingering.
我是医疗官快去吧！
I'm the medical officer. Get cracking!
有人愿意告诉我为什么他想建一座真的大桥吗？
Will someone tell me why he wants to build a proper bridge?
不要担心老尼克他知道自己在干什么
Don't worry about old Nick. He knows what he's doing.
嘿 柯林普顿该给我们展示一下了
Hello, Clipton. About time you paid us a visit.
我们的小伙子干得真不错
Fine job our chaps are doing.
是的 他怎么样？
Yes. How's he behaving?
当我们接管过来以后 他已经变得很讲理了
He's been most reasonable since we took over.
- 他在想什么？ - 我不清楚
- What's he thinking? - I haven't the foggiest.
- 谢谢你 里夫 - 好的 长官
- Thanks, Reeves. - Right, sir.
你怎么看？
What do you think?
绝对是个挑战 对不对？
Quite a challenge, isn't it?
你真认为建这座桥是个好主意吗？
Are you convinced that building this bridge is a good idea?
- 你是认真的吗？ - 是的 长官
- Are you serious? - Yes, sir.
一个好主意吗？ 我们再看看
A good idea? Take another look.
你不认为他们士气很高吗？ 你不认为军纪又得到恢复了吗？
You don't agree morale is high? Discipline has been restored?
你不认为他们的待遇得到提高了吗？
Their condition has improved?
他们难道没有更快乐了一些了吗？
Are they a happier lot or aren't they?
他们吃得也好了 再也得不到虐待
They feed better and they are no longer abused.
坦率地说 柯林普顿 有时我一点也不了解你
Honestly, Clipton, there are times when I don't understand you at all.
让我说得更清楚一些
I'll try to make myself clear.
事实上 我们所作的事情可以被理解为…
The fact is, what we're doing could be construed as...
…对不起 长官 是通敌合作
...forgive me, sir, collaboration with the enemy.
甚至可以被认为是叛国罪
Perhaps even treason.
我们是战俘 我们没有权利拒绝劳动
We're prisoners of war. We haven't the right to refuse to work.
我知道 长官 但是我们一定要做得这么好吗？
I understand that, sir. But must we work so well?
我们一定要做得比他们自己还好吗？
Must we do better than they could themselves?
如果你替Saito做手术 你是会尽力治好他还是杀死他？
If you had to operate on Saito, would you do your best or let him die?
你难道不认为懒散会击垮我们？
Would you prefer we disintegrate in idleness?
让世人说我们连一件正常的工作都不会做？
Or have it said we can't do a proper job?
这很重要 要让他们知道 他们不可能在身体或精神上打垮我们
It's important to show them they can't break us in body or in spirit.
好好看看 柯林普顿
Take a good look, Clipton.
有一天 当战争结束
One day the war will be over.
我希望将来那些使用这座桥的人…
I hope that those who use the bridge in years to come...
…会记住它是怎么样被建成的 是谁修建了他们
...will remember how it was built, and who built it.
不是一群奴隶 而是一群战士 是一群英国战士 甚至是在被俘的情况下修建的
Not a gang of slaves, but soldiers. British soldiers, even in captivity.
- 是的 长官 - 你是一个好医生
- Yes, sir. - You're a fine doctor...
但是对于战争 你还要学习很多
...but you've a lot to learn about the army.
抓住他！ 抓住他！
Hold him! Hold him!
用脚！
Use your boot! Get your boot in there, will you?
早上好！
Good morning!
你们到底在看什么？
What on earth are you people staring at?
用脚踹倒他！
Get him with your boot!
对不起我来迟了 长官
I'm sorry I'm late, sir.
迟到4分钟 你在做内科检查吗？
Four minutes, to be exact. You were in need of medical attention?
- 对不起 长官？ - 我是指那个女护士
- Sir? - I was referring to the nurse.
足智多谋 华登 说的一点也不错
Very ingenious. Warden was right.
请坐
Sit down.
我请你来这里 是要你挑选行动小组里的第四个人
I asked you here to help us pick the fourth member of your team.
- 请乔伊斯先生进来 - 是的 长官
- Ask Mr. Joyce to come in. - Yes, sir.
查普曼想要乔伊斯 但是我有疑虑
Chapman wants Joyce, but I have my doubts.
他有太多的想象力了
He has too much imagination as distinct from cold calculation.
我已经告诉过你…
I've told you...
…在这个任务中 总会有万一
...in this job, even when it's finished there's always one more thing to do.
他在学校里是游泳最好的
He's the best swimmer in the school.
我早已清楚你的观点 我现在要舍尔斯的意见
I'm well aware of your evaluation. The opinion I want is Shears'.
好的 稍息
All right, at ease.
这些人想带你到雨林一游
These men are thinking of taking you for a hike in the jungle.
是的 长官
Yes, sir.
你在蒙特利尔是个会计师？
You were an accountant in Montreal?
是的 长官 但还不是个正式的会计师
Yes, sir. Not really an accountant.
因为我还没有得到许可证
That is, I didn't have my charter.
那么你实际上做什么呢？
Exactly what did you do?
嗯 长官 我只是核算数据…
Well, sir, I just checked columns and columns of figures...
…核算那些别人核算过的数据…
...which people had checked before me...
…然后别人再核算我核算过的数据
...and other people checked them after I had checked them.
- 听起来很烦人 - 长官 是很烦人
- Sounds a frightful bore. - Sir, it was a bore.
你怎么会在这里的？
How did you wind up here?
1939年 我去伦敦应征 后来 我志愿来到这里
In '39 I came over to London to enlist. Later I volunteered for this work.
- 你是志愿的！ - 是的 长官 你看 正规部队…
- You volunteered! - Yes, sir. See, the regular Army...
请继续 你可以很坦率地说
Go ahead, you can be frank.
嗯 正规部队使我回想起我原来的工作
Well, the regular Army reminded me of my job in civilian life.
他们不需要你去思考
They don't expect you to think.
那你思考这个看看
Think about this.
你能用它来杀人吗？
Are you sure you'd be able to use it in cold blood?
我知道怎么使用它
I know how to use it.
不是那意思 我问你能用它来杀人吗？
That's not what I meant. Could you use it in cold blood?
你可以毫不犹豫地杀人吗？
Could you kill without hesitation?
这个问题我曾经问过自己 它很困扰我
That's a question I've asked myself. It's worried me quite a bit.
那么答案是什么？
And what was the answer?
事实上 我并不知道答案 长官
I don't honestly know, sir.
我曾经试图想象自己…
I've tried to imagine myself....
我很难使自己相信杀戮不是犯罪
I suppose I find it hard to kid myself that killing isn't a crime.
那是军队里的一个古老的问题
It's an old army problem.
嗯 好了 谢谢你 乔伊斯
Well, I think that's all. Thank you, Joyce.
我可以参加行动了吗？
Am I to go with the team?
我们会让你知道的
We'll let you know.
你们看到了吧
You see what I mean.
嗯 至少他是诚实的
Well, at least he was honest.
不到那时候 我们谁也不知道答案
None of us ever know the answer to that question until the moment arises.
你的意见呢 舍尔斯？
What's your opinion, Shears?
嗯 他是加拿大人
Well, he's Canadian.
正好吻合我们这个多国组合行动
That fits with the international composition of this outfit.
如果他想去 他可以替我去！
If he wants to go, he can take my place!
嗯 如果大家都同意乔伊斯去 那就让他们参加吧
Well, if you're all agreed on Joyce, he's yours.
我们对那个村庄进行了空中侦察
I had an air reconnaissance report on the village.
你们可以在晚上空降到那里
There's enough clearing to make your jump at dusk.
- 你经过跳伞训练吗？ - 没有 长官
- You've had parachute training? - No, sir.
该死！ 这个可麻烦了
Blast! This is awkward.
从来没遇到过这样的事情！
Silly, it never occurred to me!
也许 我可以不…
Well, maybe...
我们可以给他安排一些训练
He's right. Arrange some practice jumps for him.
我现在就去安排
I'll go check right away.
- 好的 查普曼 你也可以走了 - 是的 长官
- All right, Chapman, you can run along. - Yes, sir.
嗯 是不是很简单？
Well, feel like a sniff of air?
是的 长官
Yes, sir.
你不知道你是多么的重要
You don't realize what a plum you are.
你熟悉那地区 你和那村庄里的人结交朋友
Your knowledge of the area, making friends in that village.
就好像整个逃跑 都是我们计划好的
It's almost as if your whole escape had been planned with us in mind.
这里有些东西 你可能会感兴趣 新的" L"药片
By the way, here's something that'll interest you. The new " L" pill.
- " L"药片？ - 致命毒药 迅速 无痛
- L pill? - L for lethal. Instant, painless.
比老的型号要好很多 当然是为了被俘时使用
Much better than the old ones. For capture, of course.
你是想告诉我不要被活捉
You're telling me not to be taken alive.
算我没说
I wouldn't recommend it.
如果你们谁受伤了 其他人会把他扔在身后的
If any of you get hurt or wounded the others will have to leave him behind.
在这次行动中 炸毁目标是第一要务
The objective comes first in our work.
你想听我对这小组的真实评价吗？ 在他们面前我没有说
You want my honest evaluation? I didn't want to say in front of them.
我明白 请讲
I understand, go ahead.
嗯 查普曼很好 在他血管里流的是冰水
Well, Chapman will be fine. Ice water in his veins.
乔伊斯 吗… 他会好的
Joyce is.... He'll be okay.
- 华登 我觉得不行 - 为什么？
- It's Warden I don't get. - Oh? Why not?
他只是个剑桥老师
Cambridge don and all of that.
他就像个玩鞭炮的孩子…
It's one thing to play with explosives like a kid with firecrackers...
他经验很丰富的
He's not without experience, you know.
当新加坡陷落的时候 他在后面炸掉了几座大桥
When Singapore fell, he stayed behind to blow up a couple of bridges.
还在小日本抓住他之前 安装了好几个装置
Many other installations before the Japs caught him.
- 真精彩 他… - 长官 有些麻烦
- Fascinating story. He... - Sir, it's most annoying.
从时间上考虑 他们认为练习跳伞意义不大
In view of time, they don't think practice jumps would be worth it.
如果你跳一次 只有50%机会受伤
If you make one jump there's only a 50?0 chance of injury.
跳两次 80% 3次 他肯定要受伤
Two jumps, 80?0. Three jumps, you're bound to get your packet.
大家的一致的结论是 最好的办法就是让舍尔斯…
The consensus is, the most sensible thing for Shears to do...
不要训练 直接去跳下去
...is to go ahead and jump and hope for the best.
带不带降落伞？
With or without parachute?
噢 很好！
Oh, very good!
带不带降落伞！
With or without!
他挂在树上！
He's in the trees!
Yai 说我们不能从你的那条路去桂河
Yai says we can't reach the Kwai your way.
有太多的日军岗哨 我们要迂回到北方穿越原始森林
There are too many Japanese patrols. We'll swing north through heavy jungle.
- 那么谁带路？ - Yai
- Then who's going to lead? - Yai.
他恨日本人 他们抓走了这里所有的男人
He hates the Japanese. They took all his men.
我们必须用妇女来帮我们搬东西
Which means we shall have to use women bearers.
- 妇女！ - 她们能胜任的
- Women bearers! - They're capable.
他说在这里过夜很危险
He says it's dangerous to spend the night here.
3里外有个日军岗哨 所以我们要在森林里睡觉了
There's an enemy post three miles away so we'll have to sleep in the jungle.
- 查普曼怎么办？ - Yai会把他和伞埋起来
- What about Chapman? - Yai will bury him and his chute.
有什么问题吗？
Is there something wrong?
我正在想你会说他们的语言 而我不会
I was just thinking. You speak Yai's language. I don't.
他要带路走我从未走过的路
He's going to lead you to the river by a route I never took.
那么还要我来干什么呢？
Will someone tell me why I'm so indispensable to this outfit?
我知道你的感受 但事情总有万一 对不对？
I know how you feel, but there's always the unexpected, isn't there?
和查普曼讲万一吧
Tell that to Chapman.
我们开始行动吧！
Let's get cracking!
你很可爱
You're lovely.
可  爱
Lovely.
工作愉快！
Be happy in your work!
是 长官
Yes, sir.
蚂蝗
Leeches.
她让你别动她会把你背上的蚂蝗弄下来
She's telling you to hold still. She'll take the leeches off your back.
象你这样的女孩怎么能在这种地方呢？
What's a girl like you doing in a place like this?
我会教你说暹罗语
I'll teach you to say that in Siamese.
不 太多的交谈会坏事
No, that would spoil it. Too much talk always spoils it.
那玩意儿怎么了？
What's wrong with that thing?
信号太弱了
It's taken an awful beating. I can't get a strong signal.
因为这里又湿又霉！ 雨林里所有的一切都是这样
I'll tell you. It's wet, mildewed! Like everything else in this jungle.
你最好把它扔掉！
You might as well dump it!
这里是东京电台 广播结束
This is Radio Tokyo signing off.
提醒您不要紧张…
This is your friendliest enemy reminding you to take it easy...
…不要盲动
...and never volunteer for anything.
如果我们还呆在这里 我们就出不去了
If we stay, we'll be up to our necks.
- 就快译好了 长官 - 快读！
- I've got it all decoded, sir. - Read it!
是 长官 "1 原来说的大桥已经不再建了
Yes, sir. "One, original bridge works reported abandoned.
在原址下游的地方 在建新的大桥
New construction downstream from first site.
2 敌人想在通车典礼上从曼谷到仰光
Two, enemy intends to open railway with passage of special train...
开出一列专列…满载军队和重要人物
...Bangkok for Rangoon with troops and V.I.P.
估计在13号上午到达目的地
Estimated to arrive target, a.m. 1 3th.
3 同时要炸掉专列
Three, synchronize demolition with passage of train.
4 好好干 玩的开心" 就是这些
Four, good hunting. Have fun." That's all.
一列火车和一座大桥！
A train and a bridge!
我们能及时赶到那里吗 长官？
Can we get there in time, sir?
Yai说我们还有2- 3天的路程
Yai says we're two to three days away.
如果我们快走的话 我们会在12号日落前赶到那里
If we set a faster pace, we could make it before sundown on the 1 2th.
搭上一列火车 很值
It's worth it for the train.
好 我们要尽一切办法 好好干 玩的开心
Oh, by all means. Good hunting. Good show.
玩的开心 干得很好
Jolly good fun. Jolly good.
如果你没有修好收音机 我们就不会知道还有一列火车
If you hadn't fixed the radio, we wouldn't know about the train.
总有万一 对不对？
There's always the unexpected, isn't there?
- 半品脱 长官 - 奎宁
- Half a pint, sir. - Quinine.
嗯 我们回头再弄
Well, we'll complete this later.
- 柯林普顿 我们遇到一个问题 - 是吗 长官？
- Clipton, we're facing a crisis. - Yes, sir?
我与里夫 和休斯谈过 我们不可能及时建好大桥
I spoke with Reeves and Hughes. We can't finish the bridge on time.
我们人力不够
We haven't the manpower.
我已经请指挥官参加劳动 但是还不够
I've asked the officers to help, but that won't do it.
指挥官也在干活？
The officers are working?
我解释了情况 他们志愿参加 但是人还不够
I explained the situation and they volunteered, but it's not enough.
为什么不向 Saito要求一些人？
Why not ask Saito for some men?
这是我们的任务 要用我们自己最大的资源
This is ours. We'll make the most of our resources.
这就是我为什么来和你谈 我要病人名单
That's why I came to talk to you. The sick list.
这里都是病人
There's not a man in this hospital who doesn't belong there.
我并不是责备你 但总有一些人要装病
It's no reflection on you, but there are always a few malingerers.
保持警惕 这就是我要说的
Keep an open mind, that's all I ask.
过来 我们来看看
Come along, let's see.
别动 别动
Don't move, don't move.
Haskins什么病？
What's wrong with Haskins?
阿米巴痢疾和发烧 104度
Amoebic dysentery and black water fever. Temperature of 1 04.
好的 我知道了
Right. I see.
这个人呢？
And this man?
腿部溃疡 如果我昨天多切一点的话 就可以保住这条腿
Leg ulcers. I may be able to save it if I do more cutting tonight.
要把他派去劳动吗？
Want to send him out to work?
不许胡说八道 柯林普顿
Don't talk rot, Clipton.
那个人呢？
That man there?
胳膊感染
His arm's infected.
这些人的伤大多数都不会彻底痊愈
Most of their wounds won't heal properly.
我在想 新鲜空气和轻微的劳动 会比关在这笼子里好些
I wonder if fresh air and light duties might do more than being cooped up.
- 轻微的劳动？ - 因为擦伤胳膊就把他放在这里…
- Light duties? - It's not our policy to keep a man...
- 不符合我们的原则 - 不符合我们的原则？
- ...just because he scratched his arm. - Not our policy?
即使状态不佳 但是还是可以利用的
A man may not be on top of his form, but he can still be useful.
比如清理焊缝啦 收拾现场啦 稍息 贝克
Trimmings and finishing jobs. Stand easy, Baker.
你想去桥上做些轻微的工作吗？
Do you feel up to doing a little light work on the bridge?
- 随您吩咐 长官 - 很好
- Anything you say, sir. - Good show.
你呢？ 有困难吗
You? Nothing difficult.
- 我会尽力 长官 - 好样的
- I'll try, sir. - Good man.
同志们 不言而喻 我以你们为荣
Look here, men. It goes without saying that I'm proud of all of you.
但是我们现在遇到困难 如果你们觉得自己能行的话
But we're facing a crisis. For those of you who feel up to it...
能援助我们一下吗？ 做一些力所能及的事情 搬搬弄弄 涂涂抹抹？
...how about lending us a hand? Fetch and carry, paint here and there?
怎么样？
What do you say?
- 是的 长官 - 好样的 跟我来吧
- Yes, sir. - Good show. Come on, follow me.
10分钟
Ten minutes.
要确认他们全都死了
Make sure they're all dead.
跟我来 乔伊斯
Come on, Joyce.
用匕首 否则我们会打到自己人
Use your knife or we'll be shooting each other.
走那边 乔伊斯
Go that way, Joyce.
我可以干掉他的 我已经准备好了
I could have done it. I was ready.
你受伤了 长官？
Are you hit, sir?
走
Let's go.
只是表面伤 不会有骨折
It's superficial. Maybe a chipped bone, but nothing broken.
- 是我的错 长官 - 噢 住嘴
- It's my fault, sir. - Oh, shut up.
我可以走的不很严重
I can walk on it. That's all that counts.
是啊 但是还有多远 我们能走多快呢？
Yeah, but how far and how fast?
不试不知道 对不对？
We won't know that till I've tried it, will we?
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
我没有命令停止
I didn't give orders for a halt.
我们都需要休息一下
We all need it.
我们还要5小时急行军才能到达目标
We're still five hours' fast march from the objective.
也许要6小时
Maybe six.
快
Come on.
如果你一直走的话 你会流血不止而死的
If you keep walking, you'll bleed to death.
- 你们必须把我留在这里 - 你停下来 我们就停下来
- You're going to leave me here. - If you stop, we stop.
你不可能在夜里研究大桥的结构
You can't study the layout of the bridge after dark.
你们必须在日落前赶到那里
You've got to get there before sundown.
但是 长官 任务结束后 我们不能保证顺这条路返回…
But, sir, when the job's done, who knows if we can return by this route...
即使我们走这条路 也不能保证找到你
...or whether we could find you if we did?
如果我是你的话 你知道的 我就一点也不犹豫就会离开你
If you were me, I wouldn't hesitate to leave you and you know that.
他不知道 但是我知道
He doesn't know, but I do.
你会把你妈妈抛弃在这里的 如果规则要求这样的话
You'd leave your own mother here if the rules called for it.
你们必须继续前进这是命令
You'll go on without me. That's an order.
舍尔斯 现在由你来指挥
You're in command now, Shears.
我不遵守这条命令
I won't obey that order.
你的英雄主义让我恶心
Your heroics make me sick.
你们都带着死亡的臭气
You carry the stench of death like the plague.
爆炸 L药片
Explosives and L- pills go well together.
不是这个就是那个 要么毁掉大桥 要么毁掉自己
It's one thing or the other. Destroy a bridge or destroy yourself.
这场战争只是个游戏
This is just a game, this war.
你和那个尼科尔森上校都有疯狂的勇气 为了什么？
You and that Colonel Nicholson. You're crazy with courage. For what?
怎样才能死的象个绅士 怎样死才符合规矩…
How to die like a gentleman, how to die by the rules...
而问题是要怎样才能象个人那样活着！
...when the only important thing is how to live like a human being!
我不会让你死在这里的 华登…
I'm not gonna leave you here to die, Warden...
因为我才不管你那个什么大桥或者你的什么规则
...because I don't care about your bridge or about your rules.
如果我们继续前进 我们就一块走
If we go on, we go on together.
老Yai 干得好
Good old Yai.
好的
All right.
快过来
Come on.
我们走近些
Let's get closer.
还在耿耿于怀我们带你一起来吗？
Still sorry we brought you along?
- 感觉好点了吗？ - 是的
- Feeling better? - Yeah.
现在还由你指挥
You're in command again, you know.
谢谢 上校
Thank you, major.
真奇怪这是一座坚固的 设计得很好的大桥
I can't understand it. It's such a solid, well- designed job.
并不象敌人一贯拼凑的的那种东西
Not like the bridges the enemy usually throws together.
看
Look.
下面那些可怜的小鬼子
Those poor devils down there.
可以想象他们被逼着在这样的条件下建桥的情景
Imagine being forced to build that in the condition they must be in.
还有英国军官在地上工作
They've got a British officer working on his knees.
小日本好像很高兴
The Japanese seem to be enjoying it too.
如果他知道我们在这里 肯定可以鼓舞他的士气
If he knew we were here, it might boost his morale.
如果不是也要炸那火车 我们就可以设置个定时炸弹 然后跑到几里之外
If not for the train, we could set a time fuse and be miles away.
我们不知道火车明天是什么时间通过这里…
Since we don't know what time it'll cross tomorrow...
我们不得不手动引爆炸药
...we'll have to do the job manually.
我们可以把炸药填在桥墩3尺水面下
We'll set the charges against the piles...
我想…
...about three feet underwater, I should think...
把主线缆布到下游引爆者那里
...and run the main wire downstream to the plunger.
问题是引爆者应该藏在哪里？
The problem is where to hide it.
我们这一边河流很显然被日军占用
Our side of the river is obviously used by the Japanese.
他们一眼就能发现
They'd spot it at once.
看 你们看到那些树段和它们下面的岩石了吗？
Look. Do you see those fallen tree trunks?
在那边的小沙滩上？
And the grey rock just below them on that little beach?
- 是的 长官 我看到他们了 - 那里就是我们的引爆位置
- Yes, sir, I see them. - That's our key position.
虽然在河的那边…
The wrong side of the river...
…但是是在有效距离内的唯一藏身之处
...but it's the only hiding place within feasible distance.
当桥被引爆之后…
As soon as the bridge goes up...
…那个人必须游回来
...whoever's there will have to swim back.
这样游泳可不好受
It won't be a pleasant swim.
长官 我的游泳技术是最好的
Sir, I was the best swimmer in my course.
看来只能是你了
It looks like your line of country, then.
谢谢
Thank you.
舍尔斯 在这个岸边找个地方掩护乔伊斯
Shears, pick a spot on our side of the bank where you can cover Joyce.
Yai会和你一起 当小日本发现乔伊斯时
Yai will be with you so you can occupy the Nips...
你们可以帮助他
...if they make trouble for Joyce.
理论上总有万一…
On the theory that there's always one more thing...
我也会在这边用迫击炮牵制他们的
...l'll set up the mortar here to create an additional diversion.
甚至我还可以对火车来几下
Perhaps I might even take a few potshots at the train.
都明白了吗？
All clear?
还有问题吗？ 好的 你天一黑就行动
Any questions? Right, you'll start as soon as it's dark.
他们肯定在桥上有岗哨…
They're sure to have sentries on the bridge...
所以你必须从上游把炸药送过去
...so you'll have to float the stuff down from upriver...
也就是说要扎一个筏子
...which means building a raft.
Yai.
Yai会带3个妇女帮助你
Yai will take three women to help you.
还有一个要和我呆在一起 好 开始行动！
One will stay here with me. All right, get cracking!
你知道 如果不是脚踝受伤 乔伊斯的任务就是我的了
You know, if it wasn't for my ankle, I'd take Joyce's assignment.
你认为他行吗？
You think he'll be all right?
我觉得可以 要我来处理吗？
I think so. Want me to handle it?
如果可以的话 我会让你和迫击炮呆在一起
I'd let you stay up here with the mortar if I could.
对不起
I'm sorry.
结束之后 我希望你能得到病休…
When it's over, I hope you get that medical discharge...
而且是毫不困难地得到
...and not the hard way.
谢谢
Thanks.
装弹
Load.
真漂亮
Beautiful.
是的 很漂亮
Yes, beautiful.
一流的工程
A first- rate job.
我从未想到会做得这么好
I had no idea it would turn out so well.
是啊 干得很漂亮
Yes, a beautiful creation.
我一直在想…
I've been thinking....
明天就是我服役28年
Tomorrow it will be 28 years to the day that I've been in the service.
28年的和平与战争
Twenty- eight years in peace and war.
我呆在家里的时间不超过10个月
I haven't been at home more than ten months in all that time.
当然 这仍然是完美的人生
Still, it's been a good life.
我热爱印度
I love lndia.
我不可能从头再来
I wouldn't have had it any other way.
但是 有时候…
But there are times....
突然你会意识到你又回到了起点
Suddenly you realize you are nearer the end than the beginning.
而你感到彷徨…
And you wonder....
你问自己…
You ask yourself...
…人生的意义是什么…
...what the sum total of your life represents...
…这样和那样又有什么差别…
...what difference your being there at any time made to anything...
...or if it made any difference at all, really.
与其他的职业比起来
Particularly in comparison with other men's careers.
我不知道这样想是否正确的…
I don't know if that kind of thinking's healthy...
但是我必须承认 我一直在思考这些问题
...but I must admit I've had some thoughts on those lines...
...from time to time.
但 今晚…
But tonight....
今晚…
Tonight....
糟糕
Blast.
我得走了
I must be off.
他们在准备一些娱乐活动
The men are preparing some sort of entertainment.
真可爱
Lovely.
如果你是
If you were the only
世上唯一的女孩
Girl in the world
你是世上唯一男孩
And you were the only boy
其他的一切都不重要
Nothing else would matter
在今天
In the world today
我们要相爱
We could go on loving
用古老的方式
In the same old way
伊甸园只是为两个人而建
A Garden of Eden just made for two
我代表大家说几句…
I'm sure I speak for all of us...
这是一个愉快的夜晚
...when I say this has been a most enjoyable evening.
明天你们大多数都要转移到一个新的战俘营 开始新的工作
Most of you move on tomorrow to a new camp and new construction.
很遗憾你们看不到大桥的首次使用
It's a pity you won't see the first practical use of this bridge.
你们会很高兴的知道这座大桥
You'll be glad to know that the completion...
所连接的铁路
...of this link in the railway...
可以让我们用火车来
...will enable us to transport the sick and disabled...
把伤病员运输到新的营地
...to the new camp by train.
Saito上校善意的允许
Colonel Saito has kindly permitted me to stay behind...
我和柯林普顿上校留在最后
...with Major Clipton and the sick men...
几天后我们就会会合
...and we'll rejoin you in a few days' time.
现在你们这里的工作已经结束了
Now that your work here is finished...
我想你们有很多人会松弛下来
...l suppose many of you feel somewhat let down.
这完全可以理解
That's quite understandable.
这是很自然的反应
It's a very natural reaction.
但是某年某月某周某天
But one day, in a week, a month, a year...
在那一天 上帝保佑 我们全部回到自己的家乡
...on that day when, God willing, we all return to our homes again...
你会对自己在这里的工作感到自豪
...you're going to feel very proud of what you've achieved here...
...in the face of great adversity.
你们所做的
What you have done should be...
我想会是
...and I think will be...
我们国民 战士和市民的榜样
...an example to all our countrymen, soldier and civilian alike.
你们光荣地生存下来
You have survived with honour.
另外
That, and more.
在这个蛮荒之地
Here in the wilderness...
你们转败为胜
...you have turned defeat into victory.
我祝贺你们
I congratulate you.
干得不错
Well done.
为了国王
To the king.
你现在就位了
You're in business.
还差什么吗？ 树干 弹药 背包 水壶 匕首
Now, you got everything? Stem, ammunition, pack, canteen, knife.
我会直接穿过河流
I'll be directly across the river.
教授说总要以防万一
The professor says there's always one more thing to do.
但我想不起来要防什么
I can't think of what it could be.
除了祝你你长命百岁
Except to wish you a long and happy life.
谢谢
Thank you.
发生了什么事情？
What's happened?
水位降低了
The river's gone down.
可以看到电线了
You can see the wire.
炸药包！
The charges!
别等火车了
Don't wait for the train.
现在引爆！
Do it now!
如果Saito是对的 火车在5到10分钟后就会过来
If Saito is correct, the train will arrive in 5 or 1 0 minutes.
如果你不介意 我想从山顶上看
If you don't mind, I'll watch from up on the hill.
为什么？ 从桥上最好
Why? It's better from the bridge.
很难解释 先生 我不想成为这典礼的一部分
It's hard to explain, sir. I'd rather not be a part of it.
随你 说真的 有时我真不了解你
As you please. Honestly, sometimes I don't understand you at all.
如你所说 长官 我还要好好学习战争
As you once said, sir, I've got a lot to learn about the army.
早上好
Good morning.
夜里水位降低了
River's gone down in the night.
他在干什么？
What's he doing?
上校 有古怪
Colonel, there's something rather odd going on.
我认为在火车到来之前 我们应该检查一下
I think we better have a look around before that train comes across.
他简直疯了
He's gone mad.
他把他带到那里去了！
He's leading him right to it!
可是我们自己人！
Our own man!
我是对的 有古怪
I was right. There is something going on.
干掉他 孩子！
You've got to do it, boy! You've got to do it now!
你有刀子吗？ 我认为大桥被下了炸药了！
Have you a knife? I just realized the bridge has been mined!
炸药！
Mined!
好小子！
Good boy!
英军指挥官！ 我来炸掉大桥
British officer! Here to blow up the bridge.
- 炸掉大桥！ - 对 长官 英军指挥部的命令
- Blow up the bridge! - Yes, sir. British commando orders.
- 炸掉大桥？！ - 是的 没有时间了！
- Blow up the bridge?! - Yes. There's no time!
不 不行！ 救命！
No, no! Help!
杀掉他！ 杀掉他！
Kill him! Kill him!
让我走 长官！ 你不明白！
Let me go, sir! You don't understand!
杀掉他！ 杀掉他！
Kill him! Kill him!
杀掉他 乔伊斯！
Kill him, Joyce!
你！
You!
我干了什么？
What have I done?
疯了！
Madness!
我必须这样做！
I had to do it!
我必须这样做！ 他们会被活捉的！
I had to do it. They might have been captured alive!
我只能那样做！
It was the only thing to do!
疯了！
Madness!